Guide to the World War II Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
World War II collection
1937-2008
1937-1946
MS 688
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
26.27
An artificial collection of publications, including propaganda, leaflets, posters, underground material, newspapers, correspondence, and memorabilia written in approximately fifteen languages from fifty nations which relate to World War II.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The bulk of the material was collected by Joseph T. Curtiss for the Yale Library Project. Transferred from Zeta Collection, 2004. Gift of Tanja Lorkovic, 2008. Gift of Robert Booth, 2008. Gift of David Wyatt Aiken, Sr., 2010.
Existence and Location of Copies
Box 42 of Series II, Leaflets, Newspapers and Reports, is available on microfilm (1 reel, 35 mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM261.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series and eleven additions: I. General Publications, 1937-1946. II. Leaflets, Newspapers, and Reports, 1941-1945. III. Civilian Correspondence, Diaries, and Memorabilia, 1937-1946.
Scope and Contents
The bulk of the material in the WORLD WAR II COLLECTION was gathered in connection with a project sponsored during the war by the United States Office of Strategic Services. This operation, called the "Yale Library Project," was devised in 1942 and had as its purpose the collection of Axis intelligence through an agent stationed in a neutral country. Joseph T. Curtiss, a professor of English at Yale University, was chosen by the OSS as the agent whose ostensible mission was to collect war propaganda for the Yale Library. He was sent to Turkey in April 1943 and until his departure in September 1945 he not only gathered material for the OSS, but also shipped two tons of war literature back to the United States. These publications were ultimately distributed among a number of interested libraries, including Yale.
Yale also received two substantial gifts of propaganda material prepared by the Psychological Warfare Branch of the Allied Expeditionary Force. Colonel Heber Blankenhorn contributed leaflets, newspapers, and brochures designed for the European theatre, while Colonel Jo Zack Miller donated several series of leaflets prepared for use in the Pacific. Other gifts have expanded the collection to include posters and memorabilia as well as printed matter.
In addition the collection includes a number of diaries, letters and reports by civilians who were in the war zones. These were sent to the Yale Library by interested alumni and others who wanted a permanent place to deposit these accounts. In 1981 all this material was brought together under the general title: World War II Collection.
The collection contains materials printed in fifteen languages from some fifty countries and gives the reader a broad sampling of the aims and propaganda appeals of both Axis and Allied governments, including governments-in-exile. The material has been divided into three series: Series I, GENERAL PUBLICATIONS; Series II, LEAFLETS, NEWSPAPERS AND REPORTS; and Series III, CIVILIAN CORRESPONDENCE, DIARIES AND MEMORABILIA.
Series I, GENERAL PUBLICATIONS is arranged alphabetically by the name of the country issuing the material and further divided by language. Occasional monographs printed independently or in scholarly journals during the war are also included, and are filed according to the country of their subject. The publications of official government agencies, governments-in-exile and of support groups abroad are all filed under the name of the country. The literature issued in Polish and English by the Polish government-in-exile, for example, as well as publications by sympathetic American Polish groups are all filed under Poland. A similar procedure was followed for the governments-in-exile of France and the Netherlands. Literature issued by the German occupation authorities in those countries will be found under "Germany - French language" and "Germany - Dutch language." The publications of the native collaborationist group in the Netherlands, however, are filed under Netherlands.
The publications of the governments-in-exile tend to be theoretical and historical in nature, while the literature issued by the governments actively engaged in the conflict is on a more pragmatic level with bulletins on how to use a gas mask, on war time nutrition, on production levels, etc. The materials for the United States and Great Britain cover ca. 10 and 4 linear feet respectively and contain civilian as well as official government materials providing an overview of life in these countries during the war. Included are campaign histories, literature issued by war protesters, government reports on domestic and foreign affairs, materials issued by war relief organizations, memoranda on post war aims and considerable material issued by civilian defense organizations.
A small number of special subjects have been interfiled among the countries in the appropriate alphabetical position. These are: Catholic Church, Concentration camps, Jews, NATO, United Nations, UNRRA, and War crimes and trials.
Series II, LEAFLETS, NEWSPAPERS AND REPORTS is made up of what were called "white bombs" i.e. propaganda leaflets dropped from airplanes and manifestos and newspapers issued by the military in the course of field operations. The series is divided into two parts. The first consists of leaflets arranged by the issuing agency or country, and grouped according to the population to which it was directed. The Allied Command, for example, issued separate literature for the German army, for German civilians and for foreign workers in Germany.
This part also contains an exceptionally complete series of leaflets issued in the last days of the campaign in the Pacific. Included are leaflets addressed to Japanese soldiers urging them to surrender, a variety of safe-conduct passes, and instructions on how to approach American army lines. There are also leaflets addressed to the civilian populations in the Philippines, Okinawa, Formosa and other islands, issued as the fighting approached these areas. Most of the leaflets and newspapers, some of which were meant to be dropped by airplane in combat areas, are accompanied by English translations. The sophisticated design and typography will be an additional source of interest to students of the period. It should be noted that this part contains publications not only by the Allies, but also leaflets issued by Germany and Japan addressed to Allied troops and urging surrender.
The second part of the series consists of newspapers and other publications issued by the advancing Allied armies after the D-Day invasion, arranged by language. Since the literature dates from the last years of the war, the items from Europe contain many news bulletins (in the leaflets as well as the newspapers) charting the daily progress of the advancing Russian and Allied armies. Also included here are reports, memoranda and manuals concerning the psychological warfare operations of the United States and of the Allied Expeditionary Force.
Series III, CIVILIAN CORRESPONDENCE, DIARIES AND MEMORABILIA consists of letters from Americans in various parts of the world to their family and friends at home relating their war experiences. The letters are arranged by the country from which they were written and come from all parts of Asia and Europe, with one letter from the Argentine Republic. Of special interest is a letter to her parents from a young girl who was in Hawaii at the time of the attack on Pearl Harbor giving a civilian report on the event. Mementoes of both German and Allied origin make up the few items of memorabilia included in this series.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
D-Day National Remembrance Day; World War, 1939-1945 -- Pamphlets; World War, 1939-1945 -- Propaganda; World War, 1939-1945 -- Protest movements; World War, 1939-1945 -- Underground literature; World War, 1939-1945; Curtiss, Joseph T., 1901-1992; Miller, Jo Zach, 1883-1970; Yale University Library. Yale Library Project
- GENERAL PUBLICATIONS, Series I
  - Albania
    - French language (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - German language (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Anti-semitism (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Argentina
    - English language (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - German language (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Spanish language (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Armenia - English language (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Australia (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
    - Armed forces (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Armed forces - Camouflage (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Armed forces - Campaign histories (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - The Australian Army at War (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - The Real Australian Soldier (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - The Jap Was Thrashed (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - The War in New Guinea (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Yanks and Aussies in Battle (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Civilian defense (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
      - New South Wales (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Queensland (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Tasmania (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Victoria (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
      - Western Australia (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Austria
    - English language (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - German language (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Postwar - German and English languages (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Baltic States - English language (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Basque Country (Euzkadi) - English language (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Belgium
    - English language (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
      General note
      See also: box 35, folder 408
    - Flemish language (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - French language (Box 2, Folder 32-33)
    - Spanish language (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - British Guiana (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Burma (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Canada - English language (Box 3, Folder 37-38)
    - Armed forces (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Civilian defense (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Political organizations
      See: box 20, folder 229
    - Postwar (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Canada - French language (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Catholic Church
    - English language (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Spanish language (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Ceylon (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - China - English language (Box 3, Folder 46)
    See also: box 35, folder 410
  - China - English language (Box 4, Folder 47-49)
    - Armed forces (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Concentration camps - English, French and German languages (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Cuba (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Czechoslovakia
    - Czech language (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - English language (Box 4, Folder 54-55)
    - English language (Box 5, Folder 56-57)
      - [Miniature pamphlets] (Box 5, Folder 58)
      - Press releases of the Czechoslovak Press bureau, N.Y. (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Denmark
    - Danish language (Box 5, Folder 60)
    - English language (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Finland - Dutch and English languages (Box 5, Folder 62)
    See also: box 35, folder 412
  - France - English language (Box 5, Folder 63-64)
    See also: box 35, folder 413
    - France Forever (Box 5, Folder 65)
    - France Forever - Speeches, articles (Box 5, Folder 66)
    - Personal narratives (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - France - French language (Box 6, Folder 68-69)
    - Campaign histories (Box 6, Folder 70)
      - De Dunkerque au Jour "J" (Box 6, Folder 70)
      - Les campagnes du Fezzan (Box 6, Folder 70)
    - Civilian defense (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - France - Portuguese and Spanish languages (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - Germany
    - Dutch language (Box 6, Folder 73-74)
    - English language (Box 6, Folder 75)
      See also: box 31, folder 352
    - English language - Propaganda (Box 6, Folder 75a)
    - Flemish language (Box 6, Folder 76)
    - French language (Box 6, Folder 77)
    - German language (Box 6, Folder 78)
    - German language - Postwar (Box 7, Folder 79)
    - Spanish language (Box 7, Folder 80)
  - Great Britain (Box 7, Folder 81)
    - Agriculture (Box 7, Folder 82)
    - Anti-German literature (Box 7, Folder 83-84)
    - Armed forces
      - General (Box 7, Folder 85)
      - RAF (Box 7, Folder 86)
      - Army (Box 7, Folder 87)
      - Marines (Box 8, Folder 88)
      - Navy (Box 8, Folder 89-90)
      - Women (Box 8, Folder 91)
    - Campaign histories - By locality
      - Air Offensive Against Germany (Box 8, Folder 92)
      - Among Those Present (Box 8, Folder 92)
      - Battle for Crete (Box 8, Folder 92)
      - The Battle of Egypt (Box 8, Folder 92)
      - The Battle of Flanders (Box 8, Folder 93)
      - The Battle of Greece (Box 8, Folder 93)
      - The Battle of the Atlantic (Box 8, Folder 93)
      - The Campaign in Greece and Crete (Box 8, Folder 93)
      - Combined Operations (Box 8, Folder 93)
      - Destruction of an Army (Box 8, Folder 94)
      - Five Graves at Nijimegen (Box 8, Folder 94)
      - Flying Bombs (Box 8, Folder 94)
      - Home from Dunkirk (Box 8, Folder 94)
      - Miracle Harbor (Box 8, Folder 95)
      - The Naval War in the Eastern Mediterranean: Sep 1939 to Mar 1941 (Box 8, Folder 95)
      - The Operations in the South-West Pacific Jan 15 - Feb 25, 1942 (Box 8, Folder 95)
      - Report on the Flying Bomb (Box 8, Folder 95)
    - Campaign histories - By unit
      - British Airborne Divisions (Box 8, Folder 96)
      - Eighth Army (Box 8, Folder 96)
      - Grenadier Guards (Box 9, Folder 97)
      - 21st Army Group and Armies under command of Field Marshall Montgomery (Box 9, Folder 97)
    - Children (Box 9, Folder 98)
    - Civilian defense (Box 9, Folder 99)
      - Air raid precautions (Box 9, Folder 100-101)
      - Shelters (Box 9, Folder 102)
      - By locality (Box 9, Folder 103)
      - Women's Voluntary Services (Box 9, Folder 104-105)
      - Welsh language (Box 10, Folder 106)
    - Colonies (Box 10, Folder 107)
    - Dissidents
      - Duke of Bedford (Box 10, Folder 108)
      - Lawton, Lancelot (Box 10, Folder 109)
      - Lee, Richard (Box 10, Folder 109)
      - Scrutton, Robert J. (Box 10, Folder 109)
      - Strickland, Sir Walter (Box 10, Folder 109)
    - Economic aspects (Box 10, Folder 110)
    - Education (Box 10, Folder 111)
    - Food question (Box 10, Folder 112)
    - Foreign policy (including: official despatches, texts of treaties, background material) (Box 10, Folder 113-114)
    - Foreign relations - Soviet Union (Box 10, Folder 115)
    - Government documents on domestic affairs (Box 10, Folder 116-117)
    - Government documents on foreign affairs (Box 11, Folder 118)
    - Industry (Box 11, Folder 119-120)
    - International affairs (Treatises) (Box 11, Folder 121)
    - International affairs (Treatises on Germany) (Box 11, Folder 122)
    - Labor (Box 11, Folder 123)
    - Legislation (Box 11, Folder 124)
    - Local histories (Box 11, Folder 125-126)
    - Media (Box 11, Folder 127)
    - Medicine and health (Box 11, Folder 128)
    - Peace - Individuals (Box 12, Folder 129)
    - Peace - Organizations (Box 12, Folder 130)
      - War Resisters International et al. (Box 12, Folder 131)
    - Pets (Box 12, Folder 132)
    - Political organizations (Box 12, Folder 133-134)
      See also: box 20, folders 230-232 box 20, folder 236
      - Liberal Party (Box 12, Folder 135)
      - National Committee for Rescue from Nazi Terror (Box 12, Folder 135)
      - National Council for Defense of Women and Children (Box 12, Folder 135)
      - British - Soviet (Box 12, Folder 136)
    - Postcards - Texts in various languages (Box 12, Folder 137)
    - Postwar aims - Economic (Box 12, Folder 138)
    - Postwar aims - Political (Box 12, Folder 139)
    - Postwar planning (Box 13, Folder 140)
    - Propaganda
      - Afrikaans language (Box 13, Folder 141)
      - Arabic language (Box 13, Folder 142)
      - Czech language (Box 13, Folder 143)
      - Dutch language (Box 13, Folder 144)
      - French language (Box 13, Folder 145-147)
      - German language (Box 13, Folder 148)
      - Greek language (Box 13, Folder 149)
      - Italian language (Box 13, Folder 150)
      - Persian language (Box 13, Folder 151)
      - Portuguese language (Box 13, Folder 152)
      - Scandinavian languages (Box 13, Folder 153)
      - Spanish language (Box 14, Folder 154-163)
    - Religious aspects (Box 14, Folder 164)
    - Religious aspects (Box 15, Folder 165)
    - Savings Program (Box 15, Folder 166)
    - Social Problems - Housing (Box 15, Folder 167)
    - Social Welfare (Box 15, Folder 168)
    - Travel guides (Box 15, Folder 169)
    - War aims (Box 15, Folder 170)
    - War art (Box 15, Folder 171)
    - War effort (Box 15, Folder 172-173)
    - War histories (Box 15, Folder 174-175)
    - War histories (Box 16, Folder 176)
    - War relief (Box 16, Folder 177)
      - British War Relief Society (Box 16, Folder 177)
      - Famine Relief Committee (Box 16, Folder 177)
      - Friends War Relief Service (Box 16, Folder 177)
      - Haldane Society (Box 16, Folder 177)
      - Jewish Fund for Soviet Russia (Box 16, Folder 177)
      - Navy, Army, Air Force Institutes (Box 16, Folder 177)
      - Pacifist Service Units (Box 16, Folder 177)
      - S.O.S. Society (Box 16, Folder 177)
      - Toc H (Box 16, Folder 177)
      - United Aid to China Fund (Box 16, Folder 177)
      - Red Cross (Box 16, Folder 178)
  - Greece
    - English language (Box 16, Folder 179-180)
      See also: box 31, folder 355 box 36, folder 420
      - War histories (Box 16, Folder 181)
    - French language (Box 16, Folder 182)
    - Greek language (Box 16, Folder 183)
  - Hungary (Box 16, Folder 184)
    See also: box 31, folder 356
  - Iceland (Box 16, Folder 185)
  - India
    - Issued by Great Britain (Box 16, Folder 186)
    - Issued by India (Box 17, Folder 187)
    - Issued by the United States (Box 17, Folder 188)
      See also: box 31, folder 357
  - Indochina - French language (Box 17, Folder 189)
  - Italy
    - English language (Box 17, Folder 190)
    - Italian language (Box 17, Folder 191)
  - Japan
    - English language (Box 17, Folder 192)
    - German language (Box 17, Folder 193)
  - Jews (Box 17, Folder 194)
    See also: box 36, folder 422
    - Jewish Army (Box 17, Folder 195)
    - Palestine - Keren Hayesod (Box 17, Folder 196)
    - Yiddish Scientific Institute - YIVO (Box 17, Folder 197)
  - Kenya (Box 17, Folder 198)
  - Korea (Box 17, Folder 199)
  - Latin America (Box 17, Folder 200)
  - Latvia (Box 17, Folder 201)
  - Lebanon - Kurdish propaganda - Arabic, English, French languages (Box 17, Folder 202)
  - Luxembourg (Box 17, Folder 203)
  - Mexico
    - English language (Box 18, Folder 204)
    - Spanish language (Box 18, Folder 205)
  - Netherlands (Box 18, Folder 206)
    See also: box 36, folder 423
    - By or about Anton Mussert (Box 18, Folder 207)
    - Colonies (Box 18, Folder 208)
    - Government-in-exile (Box 18, Folder 209)
      - Issued by Netherlands Information Bureau, New York (Box 18, Folder 210)
    - Humor (Box 18, Folder 211)
    - National-Socialistische Beweging in Nederland (Box 18, Folder 212-213)
    - Posters (explanation on reverse side in English) (Box 19, Folder 214)
    - Postwar planning (Box 19, Folder 215)
    - Postwar publications (Box 19, Folder 216)
    - Pro-German literature (Box 19, Folder 217-218)
    - Resistance movement (Box 19, Folder 219)
    - Underground literature (Box 19, Folder 220)
  - New Zealand (Box 19, Folder 221)
  - Nicaragua (Box 19, Folder 222)
  - Nigeria (Box 19, Folder 223)
  - Northern Rhodesia (Box 19, Folder 224)
  - Norway
    - English language (Box 19, Folder 225-226)
      See also: box 36, folder 424
    - French language (Box 20, Folder 227)
  - Philippines (Box 20, Folder 228)
    See also: box 36, folder 425
  - Poland
    - English language - Published in Canada (Box 20, Folder 229)
    - English language - Published in Great Britain (Box 20, Folder 230-232)
      For Jews in Poland - See Jews
      See also: Concentration camps
      Catholic Church - See Catholic Church - Spanish language
    - English language - Published in the United States (Box 20, Folder 233-234)
      See also: box 36, folder 426
    - French language (Box 20, Folder 235)
    - Polish language - Published in Great Britain (Box 20, Folder 236)
    - Polish language - Published in Great Britain (Box 21, Folder 237)
    - Polish language - Published in the United States (Box 21, Folder 238)
    - Spanish language (Box 21, Folder 239)
  - Portugal (Box 21, Folder 240)
  - Reconstruction - German language (Box 21, Folder 241)
  - Romania (Box 21, Folder 242)
  - Russia
    - English language (Box 21, Folder 243)
      See also: box 12, folder 136 box 32, folder 363 box 36, folder 427
    - French language (Box 21, Folder 244)
    - Bulgarian language (Box 21, Folder 245)
    - Postwar - English language (Box 21, Folder 246)
    - Postwar - German language (Box 21, Folder 247)
  - Scandinavia
    See: box 32, folder 366
  - Scotland (Box 21, Folder 248)
  - Social Democratic Party (Box 21, Folder 249)
  - South Africa - Afrikaans language (Box 21, Folder 250)
  - Spain (Box 21, Folder 251)
    See also: box 36, folder 428
  - Supreme Allied Command (Box 21, Folder 252)
  - Sweden
    - English language (Box 22, Folder 253)
    - Swedish language (Box 22, Folder 254)
  - Ukraine - English language (Box 22, Folder 255)
  - United States
    - Miscellaneous pamphlets (Box 22, Folder 258)
    - Anti-war literature (Box 22, Folder 259)
    - Anti-war organizations (Box 22, Folder 260)
      - America First Committee (Box 22, Folder 260)
        - Speeches by Charles A. Lindbergh and R. E. Wood (Box 22, Folder 261)
        - Did You Know. No. 3-28, 1941 Jun 26 - Oct 25 (Box 22, Folder 262)
        - Leaflets, speeches (Box 22, Folder 263)
    - Armed forces
      - General - Manuals (Box 22a, Folder 264)
      - Air Force (Box 22a, Folder 265)
      - Army (Box 22a, Folder 266-267)
        - Manuals (Box 23, Folder 268)
      - Army Air Forces (Box 23, Folder 269-270)
      - Coast Guard (Box 23, Folder 271)
      - Marine Corps (Box 23, Folder 272)
      - Navy (Box 23, Folder 273)
      - Women's Army Corps (Box 23, Folder 274)
      - Entertainment (Box 23, Folder 275-276)
      - Indians (Box 24, Folder 277)
      - Jews, Negroes (Box 24, Folder 278)
      - Quartermaster Corps (Box 24, Folder 279)
      - Regimental histories
        - Army Air Force units (Box 24, Folder 280)
        - 1st to 12th Armored divisions [broken set]
          - 1 - 4 (Box 24, Folder 281)
          - 5 - 12 (Box 24, Folder 282)
        - 1st to 358th Infantry divisions [broken set]
          - 1-74 (Box 24, Folder 283)
          - 75 - 100 (Box 24, Folder 284)
          - 104 - 358 (Box 24, Folder 285)
        - Miscellaneous units (Box 24, Folder 286)
        - Special branches (Box 25, Folder 287)
        - U.S. Bases (Box 25, Folder 288)
      - Religion (Box 25, Folder 289)
    - Campaign histories
      - Europe
        - American Army in Europe (Box 25, Folder 290)
        - The Last Phase - Allied Victory in Western Europe (Box 25, Folder 290)
        - Mission Accomplished - Campaigns of the VII Corps U.S.A. in the War Against Germany 1944-1945 (Box 25, Folder 290)
        - 19 Days - From the Apennines to the Alps (Box 25, Folder 291)
      - Pacific
        - The Battle for Guam (Box 25, Folder 292)
        - One Year - The Ryukyus in War and Peace (Box 25, Folder 292)
        - To the Philippines (Box 25, Folder 292)
        - Your Victory - unofficial history of Mid-Pacific War (Box 25, Folder 292)
      - Special units
        - History Delta Base Section (Box 25, Folder 293)
        - The Loss of "The Mariner" (Box 25, Folder 294)
        - OWI in ETO (Box 25, Folder 294)
        - Tankers in Tunisia (Box 25, Folder 294)
        - U.S. Strategic Bombing Survey: Summary Report (Box 25, Folder 294)
          - 1. European War (Box 25, Folder 294)
          - 2. Pacific War (Box 25, Folder 294)
        - War and the Weather (Box 25, Folder 294)